<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three great overthrovves one in the Palatinate, against Monsieur Tilley, the Duke of Bauaria's generall: giuen by the king of Bohemia himselfe, being in person in the same battell, with Sir Horatio Vere, but not Count Mansfield, as is reported, hee being at the same time in Spiers. The other before Haggenaw, against Leopaldus forces, the emperours brother, by Count Mansfields garrisons, left in the same citie. The last in Languedock in France, against the Kings forces, since Soubrizes defeat by his brother the Duke of Rohan, who hath taken Memorancy the admirall prisoner. Collected out of two letters, the one sent from Heydelburgh, the other from Mainhime, by an expresse post, that arriued here on May day at night.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08156</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18507.44</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S102342</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99838129</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99838129</idno>
            <idno type="VID">2489</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08156)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 2489)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1475-1640 ; 1075:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three great overthrovves one in the Palatinate, against Monsieur Tilley, the Duke of Bauaria's generall: giuen by the king of Bohemia himselfe, being in person in the same battell, with Sir Horatio Vere, but not Count Mansfield, as is reported, hee being at the same time in Spiers. The other before Haggenaw, against Leopaldus forces, the emperours brother, by Count Mansfields garrisons, left in the same citie. The last in Languedock in France, against the Kings forces, since Soubrizes defeat by his brother the Duke of Rohan, who hath taken Memorancy the admirall prisoner. Collected out of two letters, the one sent from Heydelburgh, the other from Mainhime, by an expresse post, that arriued here on May day at night.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[3], 6-22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>And now published [by B. Alsop] this third of May,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London] :</pubPlace>
                  <date>MDCXXII [1622]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC; NUC Pre-1956 suggests J. Dawson as printer.</note>
                  <note>Formerly STC 18923.</note>
                  <note>Identified as STC 18923 on UMI microfilm.</note>
                  <note>Title page marked, with slight loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Sion College. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Thirty Years' War, 1618-1648 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:2489:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2489:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE GREAT OVERTHROVVES ONE In the Palatinate, againſt Monſieur <hi>Tilley,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Bauaria's</hi> Generall: Giuen by the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> himſelfe, being in Perſon in the ſame Battell, with Sir <hi>Horatio Vere,</hi> but not Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> as is reported, hee being at the ſame time in <hi>Spiers.</hi> THE OTHER Before <hi>Haggenaw,</hi> againſt <hi>Leopaldus</hi> Forces, the Emperours Brother, by Count <hi>Mansfields Gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſons, left in the ſame Citie.</hi> THE LAST In <hi>Languedock</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> againſt the Kings Forces, ſince <hi>Soubizes</hi> Defeat by his Brother the Duke of <hi>Rohan,</hi> who hath taken <hi>Memorancy</hi> the Admirall Priſoner. Collected out of two Letters, the one ſent from <hi>Heydelburgh,</hi> the other from <hi>Mainhime,</hi> by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe Poſt, that arriued here on May day <hi>at Night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now publiſhed this third of May, MDCXXII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account">
            <pb facs="tcp:2489:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:2489:2"/>
            <head>MATTERS CON<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CERNING THE PALATI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NATE, WITH THE DEFEAT of Monſieur <hi>Tilley</hi> in the Palatinate, and the Duke of Memorancy in <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are two ſorts of men in the world, compared to tame and wilde beaſts, and theſe are flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers and detractors, and that wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily: For what vice may he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dominant in a Prince, or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth, which a flatterer can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not guild ouer with the faire appearance and colours of vertue: and what buſineſſe can preſent it ſelfe on the ſtage of this world, but a detractor will calum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niate and deſire it; which is more apparant at this in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant in the combuſtions of <hi>Europe,</hi> then euer was heard of in many ages: for how many be there that ſooth vp the humour of ſome kings (beſides the Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuites, whoſe profeſſion is blinde ignorance, and ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitious zeale, euen to ſet forward impietie) to ſtand vpon termes of ſoueraigntie and imperiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as is great reaſon in Monarchies, though the ſubiects be ſlaughtered, the countrey deuaſted, the people mangled, the peace dilacerated, the Churches abandoned, religion defaced, and God blaſphemed: and how many be there that diſcredit the cauſe of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:2489:3"/> diſtreſſed Princes, and the thriuing of religious buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, although the finger of God doth point it out that fairer daies ſhall follow ſtormy weather, which is moſt apparant concerning the <hi>Bohemian</hi> affaires, and the <hi>Palatinates</hi> recouery, wherein both flatterer and detractor ſtep on the ſtage of this world to act their Scenes with deceitfull hurts and malitious in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents. The flatterer carryed away with outward ſhowes of the Papacy, and <hi>Catholicke</hi> Princes, will not apprehend, that there can be any determination of their greatneſſe, but cry out with <hi>Nabuchadnezer</hi> to worſhip the golden image of their Monarchy. The detractor ſhaking his head, and biting his lip at any ſucceſſe ſhall happen, and deriding the buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, as if the Gyants attempted to fight againſt hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen. Thus haue they magnified the houſe of <hi>Auſtria</hi> and the proceedings of the Empire: thus haue they diſcredited the King of <hi>Bohemias</hi> attempts, and ſet ſtrange characters on his actions.</p>
            <p>But as in all diſputations there is a Moderator: ſo would I might now meete with ſuch men, as will ſtand Neuters, and neither preuaricate iudgement, nor ouerthrow veritie: and if the higher matters are too tranſcendent for their capacitie, yet let them giue way to true relations, and honeſt reports, without ſcornes, or cachinations: but becauſe I ſhall neuer haue my expectation ſatisfied in this kind in regard of the multiplicy of humours in a common wealth, I leaue them all to bee deceiued themſelues, or deceiue others, and onely apply my ſelfe in this diſcourſe to ſuch men, who out of ciuill honeſtie entertaine good newes with ioy, and welcome bad
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:2489:3"/> with commiſeration and pittie, making this vſe of both, that God is the manifeſter of his owne iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and mercy to all the world. And ſo to the bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſſe in hand, and to tell you what hath hapned of late in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> ſince the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> came there, and chanced in other places as the cauſe hath thriued, and men haue had their mindes ſtirred vp with good affections.</p>
            <p>Know then, that the fifteenth of our Aprill, and the fiue and twentieth <hi>Stilo nouo,</hi> 1622. there came letters from <hi>Stuchgaret,</hi> that a thouſand horſe, and foure thouſand foote of Duke <hi>Weymers</hi> of <hi>Saxony</hi> arriued at <hi>Laffen</hi> ouer the Neckar, who brought word that the next day there will be alſo 3000. at <hi>Rottenburg</hi> for the Marqueſſe of <hi>Baden,</hi> who co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth in perſon to ſet forward the <hi>Bohemian</hi> cauſe. But the ſame day there was a mixture with as bad newes: for they will haue it that Generall <hi>Tilley</hi> came to neather <hi>Gemunds</hi> a prety great towne, and as hee ſerued the peaſants in the villages, ſo he vſed the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in this place, killing all the ſouldiers, ſlaughtring moſt part of the Burghers, torturing the preachers, and ſparing neither Captaine nor officers, nay the very ſchollers were ſubiect to his fury, ſo that it ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med he was either blinde with ignorant zeale, or mad with intemperate rage.</p>
            <p>A little before <hi>Leopaldus</hi> had ſent downe a 1000. ſouldiers into his countrey, who had paſſage euen by permiſſion of the people and ſome towne garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſond with <hi>Mansfields</hi> men to march ouer the bridge toward <hi>Haggenaw,</hi> and I muſt confeſſe, that though
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:2489:4"/> 
               <hi>Leopaldus</hi> hath beene much diſappointed in his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpectation for diuers troopes out of <hi>Italie,</hi> and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney from <hi>Spaine,</hi> yet came their ſouldiers dayly from <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and certaine companies of <hi>Swiſs</hi> are ready to marſhall a prety army in <hi>Alſatia,</hi> had not the the garriſon of <hi>Haggenaw</hi> made a fearefull ſalley vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſome ſcattered troopes, killed diuers ſouldiers, and brought eight Captains of horſe into the towne, which when the reſt vnderſtood, whom <hi>Mansfield</hi> had placed in the villages, and loath to be behinde their fellowes in glorious exploytes and profitable booty, they likewiſe drew to a head of three thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, and approched a village in which were fifteen-hundred of <hi>Leopaldus</hi> men, whom they not onely frighted with an alarum, but diſcomfited with a great ſlaughter, taking ſome priſoners, and many armes: but you muſt know in theſe diſaſters it is farre better here then with Monſieur <hi>Tilley,</hi> becauſe the ſouldiers haue an ordinary ranſome, and vpon ſurpriſals, there is an ordinary deliuery, wherein and whereby Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> hath gotten ſuch a reputation for the faire ſparings of all people that ſubmit, or yeeld him con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tribution, that the better ſort commended his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcretion and military cuſtomes, and inferiors pray for his ſucceſſe and augmentation of honour, eſpecially clap their hands for ioy, when they heare him cry out for the Coſpell, and the King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi> Yea I will be bold to ſay that theſe warres haue made more true hearted Proteſtants, then all the flatteries of Peace, and wantonneſſe of proſperitie could euer doe.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:2489:4"/>
            <p>Much about this time (and here I pray you par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don me for precedencie of Dayes, or Actions; for I would be loth to tye you or my ſelfe to ſuch ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: it is ſufficient, that you ſhall receiue the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations fully, honeſtly, and truely, as they chaunced) And ſo I ſay, much about this time Count <hi>Mans<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>field</hi> came to <hi>Germiſhem</hi> with three Regiments, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther alſo repaired Monſieur <hi>Rauillau,</hi> to treat with him about matter of great importance, eſpecially a Truce: but hee now anſwered, that hee could not determine of any thing, vntill the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> were ſetled, who ſhould diſpoſe of Buſineſſe at his owne pleaſure.</p>
            <p>Vpon the necke of this, as wee ſay, there came aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Badens</hi> preparation to the Warre: who ſent word, that his Armie was in a readineſſe, but hee would willingly haue a Campe at <hi>Durmiſhem,</hi> as being able to keepe the Field him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, hauing leuied Souldiers, and trayned Bands, to the number of ten thouſand, beſides Waggons and Munition, Carriages and Pioners, with all other Furniture belonging to a great Captaine: Nay, his Cuſtomes were ſo Religious, that in the middeſt of his Troupes hee obſerued the Sabboth, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded both Prayer and Faſting for one Meale in the ſame, whenſoeuer hee determined any Attempt, or ſet himſelfe a-worke for befitting Enterpriſes. To this you may adde the Arriuall of Palatine <hi>Lodo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wick Phillips</hi> at <hi>Germerſteme,</hi> and many Friends in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther places, as true fore-runners of the King of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemia's</hi> comming indeed.</p>
            <pb n="10" facs="tcp:2489:5"/>
            <p>Monſieur <hi>Tilley</hi> all this while ranged vp and downe, and ſometimes ſhewed his Horſe in the Fields before <hi>Ladenberg,</hi> and ſometimes came with his Foot to giue Alarums to <hi>Heydelberg,</hi> and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times terrified the Townes with diuers Outrages, and at all times watched opportunitie, to be reuen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> or at leaſt to take him at aduantage in ſome Expedition, that hee might ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge hee had a Souldier to his Aduerſarie, and as great a deſeruer of Renowne as himſelfe: In which courſes hee continued, to the affrighting both of Townes, Villages, People, and the whole Armie, till the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> came indeede; by whoſe occaſion, the ſecond Battaile, which is promiſed you, chanced, as you ſhall heare here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after; though for my part I could bee contented with the Title of a Skirmiſh. The denomination of Battaile carryes too much terror with it, and too much curioſitie of diſtinction, as beeing the higheſt part of Militarie Diſcipline: in which, many circumſtances are to bee conſidered, as mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall Agreement, a Day appointed, the Trenches caſt open, the maine Forces vnobſcured, the Troopes orderly marſhalled, the Cannon placed, and in a word, a preparation made to Death and Slaughter, as you ſee a Feaſt appointed to entertaine ſome great Prince.</p>
            <p>Now came the time, the long-wiſhed time of the arriuall of the King into the Palatinate, about which there is ſome diſparitie of reports. For ſome will haue his Armie to meet him after his Conuoy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:2489:5"/> from the Duke of <hi>Bulloigne:</hi> Some ſay, hee tooke Waggon, for the eaſe and accommodating his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and ſome ſay, hee out-ſtripped the Armie, and came onely with three Poſt-horſe to <hi>Gernſhem,</hi> from whence, hee ſpent three ſeuerall dayes in viſiting <hi>Mainhem, Franckendale,</hi> and <hi>Heydelberg:</hi> in all which places, according to the common acclamations in welcomming their Princes, as their Ioy exceeded, their Ceremonies augmented; and the Prince ſaw plainly, it was no common cuſtome of the peoples welcomming their Princes, whoſoeuer they be, but a heartie deſire to ſhew their loue and obedience vnto him, who had ventured his life to come amongſt them, and would neuer deſiſt, till they were recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penced for their loſſes.</p>
            <p>But it was too ſoone to begin ſo effectually, and ſo there paſſed at this time a reciprocal thankfulneſſe and ceremonie betweene them: yet in my conſcience it lacked ſome feruency, becauſe the ignorant people imputed ſome vnkindneſſe vnto him, in regard that by his forſaking of them, they were compelled to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake their houſes, and inheritances, to leaue them to a ſtrangers vſurpation. But this aſperſion was quickly wiped away with a gentle hand of obſeruation, and a preſent entertaining of new ioy, eſpecially that they now hoped, that theſe ſtrange Harpies which deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red their plentie, ſhould eyther bee expulſed by the valour of <hi>Zetes</hi> and <hi>Culines,</hi> or enforced to a compo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, which might deliuer euery one his portion a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: which although it ſeemed now a little dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, yet they well hoped, time and good husbandry
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:2489:6"/> would reduce to her priſtinate fulneſſe and hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomeneſſe: To which they were the rather induced, becauſe the Marqueſſe of <hi>Baden</hi> hath much augmen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Count <hi>Mansfields</hi> Army, by vniting their For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces together, and viſiting King <hi>Frederick,</hi> who can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſaluted otherwiſe, nor receiue any Character, then the King of <hi>Bohemia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>When theſe Princes were thus ſolemnly met, and that a Councell of Warre had reſolued on ſome things worthy their preſence, and ſo great an Army; Monſieur <hi>Rauille</hi> was diſcharged, and ſent home without an anſwer: For they were reſolued to haue no Peace, but to make way to new fortunes by ſharpe Swords.</p>
            <p>In the meane while that theſe things paſſed in the Palatinate, <hi>Bauaria</hi> ſuſpecting the worſt, had ray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed more Forces of his owne, and had more ſent him by the Emperour: ſo that there departed from <hi>Vppenhem</hi> ouer the Bridge eleuen Troupes of Horſe into the Lantgraue of <hi>Darmſtadts</hi> Countrey, to ioyne with <hi>Tilley</hi> at <hi>Simpen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus nothing was expected, but Miſchiefe, and Reuenge on all ſides: For no body durſt looke out of <hi>Laudenberg,</hi> by reaſon of the Horſemen of <hi>Heydelberg,</hi> which watched them continually; nor was there now any thing thought vpon, but watch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing one another, to take aduantage for their owne ends and purpoſes.</p>
            <p>And in this manner ſtood the Buſineſſe of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latinate at this houre; and ſo muſt reſt a while, till you heare the newes of <hi>Sileſia.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:2489:6"/>
            <p>The Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> ſomewhat troubled, that <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatia</hi> was denyed him by the Emperour, remained rather diſcontented then pleaſed, and ſo gaue way to the Princes of <hi>Sileſia</hi> to cal a Diet becauſe of the vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rores. For the ſouldiers had muſtred themſelues to aſſault <hi>Glatz:</hi> but were repulſed by the yong Earle of <hi>Thorn,</hi> who ſlue many of them, and made them retire with great loſſe, whereupon to preuent the worſt, he entertained 150. ſouldiers more, who came from <hi>Wittingham,</hi> by which occaſion they are ſo ſtrength<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and hartned, that they haue proteſted to defend themſelues to the laſt man. In like manner the other Proteſtants are much incenſed againſt the Biſhops, and euery where there is crying out vpon the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lickes tyranny, and wicked Ieſuites: whereupon the Biſhop of <hi>News</hi> will take from them of <hi>Cuntele</hi> the vſe of their Churches, prohibite their aſſemblies, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny the reading of the Scriptures, and as ill as <hi>Iulian</hi> the Apoſtate, debarre the intercourſe of Chriſtians: now <hi>Cuntele</hi> is three mile diſtant from <hi>Meuſe,</hi> and was euer a priuiledged place, whither they of the religion reſort, and were prowd againe to be reputed Proteſtants. For although in theſe places there was ſome diſparity betweene the Caluiniſts and Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans, which bred ſome ſcandall to the profeſſors: yet were they all glad of the generall title of Proteſtants, as you ſee at this houre, the Papiſts generally reioyce at the name of Catholicke: from the Biſhops exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple many Prieſts and officialls performed the like, but the people vnaccuſtomed to ſuch indignities, from murmuring fell to oppoſition, and ſo ſtood vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a guard of defence, and began ſome ſlender oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:2489:7"/> in many places, reſorting to the Princes and Lords of the Prouince both in towne and villages, deſiring them to let them haue the freedome of their ſoules, how euer the Emperour or Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> vnder him would ſeeme to command their bodyes, and obedience to extraordinary contributions: vpon this there is great muſtring of ſouldiers round about and the Emperour ſent a new meſſenger to the Duke of <hi>Saxony</hi> to bee carefull of the gouernment. For he knew the loſſe of <hi>Bohemia</hi> depended vpon the abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute reuolt of <hi>Sileſia:</hi> But the truth is, they were affrayde of the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ieggendorff</hi> euerie where, who for all the Parliament of <hi>Hunga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie,</hi> and the great aſſembly there to rectifie the diſorders of the Common-wealth, grew ſtrong with new forces, and was reputed twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie thouſand, and feared to come againſt them preſently: For the countrey grew mutinous, and euery man ſuſpected one another, conſidering the Emperour was reputed weake, and would glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly haue a peace, if hee knew which way to obtayne it with his honour: to which I am the rather induced, becauſe new Souldiers muſt haue money and good entertainment, and the old were worne out with many and diuers difficul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; eſpecially ſlaughter, hunger and ſickeneſſe; beſides the Countreys lay waſted where they quartered, and the Inhabitants did not husband nor till their grounds as they were woont in former times: and this was the generall cauſe almoſt throughout all <hi>Germanie,</hi> at which the people euery where were very much mooued, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:2489:7"/> troubles aroſe not for Religion or the Goſpels ſake as the maine poynt of the ſame: but for ambitious titles, and matters of State and gouernement, of which there is neither time nor occaſion to diſpute heere: and thus much for the remoter places.</p>
            <p>Now wee may draw neere home, and come to that you deſire, the ſecond Skirmiſh I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed you, which was againſt Monſieur <hi>Tilley</hi> in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> and concerning which there are diuers reports: but this Letter is come from <hi>Crutſnach,</hi> wherein the Spaniards lie in Garriſon, and therefore I am perſwaded they would make the beſt of a buſineſſe againſt them, and bee as ſparing as they could to diſcredit their owne affayres, and ſo they tell the tale in this manner.</p>
            <p>Although the Report of the King of <hi>Bohe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mias</hi> comming into the <hi>Palatinate</hi> was quickely divulged, and made knowne to all the Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, eſpecially <hi>Openhem</hi> and <hi>Crutſnach,</hi> where the Spaniards lay, and had laine euer ſince their comming into the Countrey: ſo that now they were very well fortified and intrenched: yet as they had beene quiet all this Winter, they were now likewiſe neuer ſtartled by the rumour, ſo that it was then ſuppoſed, that they had ſome priuate or ſecret directions ſo to doe, or knew there was ſome capitulation about their remouing and rendition of the place: notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding <hi>Bauaria</hi> would not bee ſo anſwered, but as the Emperour had giuen him the Countrey, he would maintaine the Title, and alſo iuſtifie the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:2489:8"/> poſſeſſion: but as you heard in many places, there came interpoſitions, and no doubt would prooue him an intruder. Beſides, when it was obiected vnto him, that although the Emperour as exaſperated a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Prince <hi>Fredericke,</hi> had done this for the preſent, and made his indignation an example of reuenge: yet either it could not laſt, or time would worke a reconciliation: but as for him, it muſt needs be a perpetuall cauſe of diſpleaſure, and their poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity in the remembrance would hunt one another in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the fields of ſlaughter and warre. To this <hi>Bauaria</hi> replyed, let hereafter times looke to themſelues, hee would not goe about to preuent deſtiny, he had now for himſelfe his limitation, &amp; therefore regarded no more, then the preſent, his owne glory, and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perors dignitie, which in his failing now muſt needs be made a ſcorne to all nations: whereupon he pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded (as you haue diuers times heard) and was in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed the onely ſupportation which his Imperiall Maieſtie truſted vnto, as affecting the reuolt of <hi>Prague,</hi> oppoſing the enemies of <hi>Bohemia</hi> and <hi>Mora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uia,</hi> repulſing the ſouldiers which had begun in <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> and now maintaining an army in the <hi>Palatinate,</hi> of which hee made Monſieur <hi>Tilley</hi> Generall, who had no queſtion deſerued well of fame and report for many ſundry actions, wherein both himſelfe and his Maſter had attained the reputation of good ſoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diers.</p>
            <p>In this courſe did they continue all this winter, repining at nothing more then the proceedings of Count <hi>Mansfield,</hi> who was now the onely barre and hindrance of their fortunes, wherefore they watched
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:2489:8"/> all opportunities to oppoſe him, but hee grew too ſtrong for them, and as I may ſay too prowd: for he left them in ſcorne to a hard winter, and made way for his owne glory, euen through the Pallaces of Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops, and countreys of Catholickes, which neither <hi>Bauaria</hi> nor <hi>Tilley</hi> could preuent. Yea, when hee had done what he liſted, he came backe againe amongſt them with greater fury and more impetuous vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, like the Ramme, which fighting with his ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſary, retireth by little and little, but not for feare or daſtardlineſſe, but to returne with greater courage and force: thus in the meane time comes the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> as I ſayd, into the <hi>Palatinate</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and found <hi>Bauaria</hi> and <hi>Tilley</hi> ſpringing with the ſpring to new vigour and luſtre, inſomuch that at two ſeuerall times <hi>Tilley</hi> had ſurpriſed ſome part of his carriages, and ſlaine ſome few of the reare of his army: yea he continued with that brauery, that hee did ſhew himſelfe moſt when the King was ſtrongeſt eſpecially after the King of <hi>Bohemia</hi> was come into the Palatinate: for then he beſtirred himſelfe indeed, and not onely ſpoyled the villages, but threatned <hi>Heydelberg,</hi> who had many alarums by his meanes, and many reports of her beſieging: not thus conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, he braued the campe himſelfe, and came out in fury to ſet vpon the King in an audacious manner, and ſo a skirmiſh began, which a little rebated his fury, but yet not eclipſed his glory.</p>
            <p>Here gentle Reader I know not what to ſay vnto thee, becauſe rumour is ſpred into ſtreames con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning this matter: but in regard my Letter comes from <hi>Crutſnach,</hi> from the Spaniards, and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:2489:9"/> that all Letters tend to one purpoſe, that there was ſuch a defeat, I will follow my Copie, let other men pleaſe themſelues as they liſt, and ſo they tell the tale thus.</p>
            <p>The King after hee had ioyned his force that <hi>Mansfield</hi> had ſent vnto him with Sir <hi>Horatio Vere,</hi> hauing occaſion to remooue his army, was purſued, or if you will, attended vpon by Monſieur <hi>Tilley,</hi> who marched along with all his forces to ouerlooke the proceedings, which was orderly performed, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till the King came to a bridge, where for the time he made a ſtand, as indeede not thinking it conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to paſſe ouer, conſidering <hi>Tilley</hi> was ſo neere, and in a valley beſide him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tilley</hi> againe coniecturing that he made this ſtay for feare of him, came the bolder forward, and preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed ſo faſt toward him, that hee was compelled to breake through a battaile of his owne pikes with his horſe, which muſt needs diſorder his foot, and which was iudiciouſly diſcouered by the King: inſomuch that being well prepared, hee tooke the aduantage, ſending ſome horſe to entertaine theſe, who came ſo forward, and aduancing with the reſt againſt the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranked pikes that could not ſo eaſily be brought in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to forme and faſhion againe, and ſo without dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling long on the buſineſſe, becauſe they continued not long in the skirmiſh, <hi>Tilleyes</hi> battle was ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne, and he himſelfe had much adoe to eſcape: then followed a ſtrange ſlaughter: for there were pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhed and taken priſoners betweene 5. or 6. thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand men, but moſt of them ſlaine, and laſt of all it ended with ſpoyle, for the ſouldiers tooke away their
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:2489:9"/> armes, and ſtripped their bodyes, leauing them na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to the fowles of the ayre. Thus is <hi>Tilley</hi> eſcaped, and therefore we can ſay no more of him: yet onely Count <hi>Mansfield</hi> is now a ſubiect to talke of, and no queſtion will run in ſome violent courſe of glory, if the Emperour doe not ſpeedily ſend more forces, and raiſe a greater army: for in my conſcience this victory hath elated him more then all his former proceedings in the Biſhopricke of <hi>Spires</hi> or <hi>Leopal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> countrey: to which I haue a faire way of beleefe, in regard that heretofore <hi>Mansfield</hi> was willing to hearken to a parley, and entertained the Emperours meſſages, and Letters about a peace: but now he gaue it out, it was onely to winne time, and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe his endes, which were to ſerue the King of <hi>Bohemia,</hi> and his comming into the Palatinate, by whom he would be both directed, and commanded, and without whoſe permiſſion he would not ſo much as conſent to a truce or ceſſation of armes.</p>
            <p>At laſt (as you haue heard) the Palatine comes vnto him, and is welcommed in euery place and applauded of all the people, ſo that it is doubted, hee will ſtand vpon the higher termes, becauſe hee hath the ſtronger force: as for the Spaniſh Garri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, they are firme and well prouided, yet I ſee no reaſon for their continuance, except <hi>Baua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria</hi> bee ſupplyed, and a new order taken to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue the warre: For whether warre or peace, I am reſolued, that Prince <hi>Frederick</hi> will not ſuffer vs thus to remaine in his countrey, and be as thorns in his ſides.</p>
            <pb n="20" facs="tcp:2489:10"/>
            <p>To this effect was the Letter from <hi>Crutſnach,</hi> writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by one of the Garriſon, and therefore I am per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded it was impartiall, and according to the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: ſo that there is hope for the generall Cauſe to thriue, and the particular Buſineſſe of the Palatinate to cheare vs with a new recouerie. And thus much for thoſe Affaires.</p>
            <p>Heere is alſo another Letter come ſecretly from <hi>Paris,</hi> concerning the Kings Forces in <hi>Languedock,</hi> which I ſuppoſe is very conuenient to be publiſhed, according to the probabilitie of the matter, and the fearefulneſſe of the Time. It is not my purpoſe to diſpute of the Actions of Princes, but to lament the poore eſtate of Proteſtants. It cannot bee hid from the eares of the World, that is not hid from the eyes of the People; and ſo, as rumour hath told vs of the diſtreſſes of the Proteſtants of <hi>France,</hi> good thoughts haue inſtructed vs to wiſh the pacification of their Troubles, and pray for the diuerſion of the Kings anger againſt them, with the ceſſation of the Warre. But it will not be: And therefore, for my part, I referre the Buſineſſe to God, who can cure the wounds of his Church, and comfort the hearts of his People, which haue of late, eſpecially in <hi>France,</hi> been more ſadded then euer before; in regard there is a Booke publiſhed in <hi>Paris</hi> of Monſieur <hi>Subizes</hi> defeat going to <hi>Rochel,</hi> whom the King followed in perſon, and ſlew many of his company: this Relation filled their ſoules with griefe, and their eyes with teares; and in ſuch a manner the ſorrow for the ſame en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed, that they would not admit of recouerie, and ioy, although they preſently heard, that Monſieur
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:2489:10"/> Duke <hi>de Rohan, Subizes</hi> Brother, being in the field for the Proteſtants in <hi>Languedock,</hi> had giuen Duke <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morancy,</hi> the Admirall of <hi>France,</hi> a great Ouerthrow, which is thus confirmed.</p>
            <p>After the Ieſuites had preuayled with the <hi>French</hi> King to goe againſt <hi>Rochel,</hi> and proſecute the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of <hi>Montalbon,</hi> the Souldiers were muſtered in euery place, and the Generall of the Armie proclay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med nothing but Warre and Deſtruction; yet was there Oppoſitions againſt them: and the Proteſtants of <hi>Prouince</hi> and <hi>Languedock</hi> well hoped, that Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſieur <hi>Deſguiers</hi> would take their Cauſe in hand, and defend their Religion; which whether he will or no, is yet doubtfull, and ſo hangs in ſuſpence.</p>
            <p>But Monſieur <hi>de Rohan</hi> would not tarry for his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution, and rayſed ſuch Forces as he could, to ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply <hi>Mountabon,</hi> and defend the Countrey: againſt whom was ſent Duke <hi>Memorancy,</hi> as Generall of the Kings Army, with other Lords and Gentlemen of qualitie; who came forward with a goodly Army, and too goodly (if it had pleaſed God otherwiſe) becauſe it was againſt their Brethren. But Kings command, and ſubiects muſt obey: <hi>Mountmorancy</hi> comes forward apace, and <hi>Mountaban</hi> was afraid of a new obſeſſion: but it proued otherwiſe. For <hi>Rohan</hi> was couragious, and preſumed on the Cauſe, though it were againſt his Prince: ſo in plaine termes (as they ſay) they fell to a Battaile; in which, all things were ordered belonging to Martiall Diſcipline, but that the Lord of Battailes did diſorder the Buſineſſe. For comming to blowes, and ioyning with furie, <hi>Memorancy</hi> gaue way, and <hi>Rohan</hi> tooke the aduan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:2489:11"/> yet the fight continued long, and till the maine Rout was too too apparant, there ſeemed no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence. But at laſt, as no extremitie can laſt, the Vic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torie fell to the Proteſtants, and the Admirall was taken priſoner, with two Brothers of his Bloud; but one of them died of his wounds, and many other were ſlaine out-right: The Letter ſayes fiue thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand, the Rumor more, but the Religious heart ſayes there were too many of theſe, conſidering the Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe was betweene Friends and Kindred, Countrey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men and of one Nation, Chriſtians and Neighbors, and not betweene Strangers and Enemies to the Kingdome.</p>
            <p>This is that wee receiue from forraine Parts, and this is that wee hearken after in our owne Countrey: euery one wiſhing well to the King of <hi>Bohemia's</hi> proceedings, euery one praying truely for the afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Churches abroad; yea, curſing the Ieſuites for ſuch a Doctrine, that bellowes out nothing but Warre and Death, Slaughter and Reuenge, Cruel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie and Spoyle, when yet the Sauiour of the World bad <hi>Peter</hi> put vp his Sword, and feed his Flocke; rode with <hi>Hoſanna</hi> and <hi>Palmes</hi> to <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> and not with Armies and Triumph; ſubmitted to Scornes and Buffetting, and did not reuenge himſelfe: And yet theſe men dare ſeduce the Princes of the World, and blaſpheme the God of Heauen, who laughes them to ſcorne for the preſent, and will in time to come caſt them in a Bed of Affliction with the Whore of <hi>Babylon.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:2489:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
